Eric Reeves Papers
© 2011 University of Connecticut
Eric Reeves Papers.
1994-2011.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Reeves, Eric, 1950-
8 linear feet.
The collection contains correspondence, emails, lectures, newspaper clippings, notes, photographs, and writings regarding Eric Reeves' advocacy, research, and analysis of the humanitarian crisis and genocide in Sudan and Darfur from 1999 onward. The collection also contains documents regarding the court case, Presbyterian Church of Sudan et al. vs. Talisman Energy Inc, Sudan.
MSS20100061
Biography
Charles Eric Reeves was born in 1950 and grew up in South Pasadena, California, the eldest of three boys and two girls. His English mother and Canadian father moved from Canada to California after World War II.
Reeves attended Williams College, in Williamstown, Massachusetts, from 1968-1972. While he had received a scholarship to assist with his living costs, he donated his funding to the Biafra Relief Fund to aid victims caught up in the civil war in Nigeria. Reeves had a student deferment during the Vietnam War; however he chose to pursue conscientious-objector status as well, and received an 1-O classification. Reeves graduated with with a bachelor’s in philosophy, and married his wife Nancy in 1973, with whom he has raised two daughters.
Reeves received his Ph.D. in Renaissance literature from the University of Pennsylvania, and in 1979 began working as a Professor of English Language and Literature at Smith College in Northampton, Massachusetts. In 1999, he began focusing full-time as a Sudan researcher and analyst, publishing extensively both in the US and internationally. He has testified several times before the Congress, has lectured widely in academic settings, and has served as a consultant to a number of human rights and humanitarian organizations operating in Sudan. Working independently, he has written on all aspects of Sudan's recent history. His book about Darfur, A Long Day's Dying: Critical Moments in the Darfur Genocide, was published in May 2007. Reeves maintains a website on Sudan documentation, http://sudanreeves.org.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, notes, photographs, writings, speeches, regarding Eric Reeves' advocacy, research and analysis of the humanitarian crisis and genocide in Sudan and Darfur from 1999 onward. The collection also contains asylum petitions from displaced Sudanese, and documents regarding the court case, Presbyterian Church of Sudan et al. vs. Talisman Energy Inc., Sudan.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into the following series:
Series I: Personal Materials ( 2002-2010 )
Series II: Writings ( 1996-2011 )
Series III: Research Files ( 1999-2009 )
Series IV: Oversize Materials ( 2004-2008 )
Series V: Audiovisual Materials ( undated [2004-2011] )
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Reeves, Eric, 1950-
Places:
Subjects:
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Audio visual materials.; Manuscripts.; Notebooks.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Notes.; Scrap-Books.; Speeches.; Newspapers.
Occupations:
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to human rights issues. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
All About Darfur. Dodd VHS 436
Ashes and Hope in Sudan’s Blue Nile. Dodd VHS 437
BBC News Panorama: China’s Secret War. Dodd DVD 136
Blood for Oil: Forgotten People of Southern Sudan. Dodd VHS 438
Child of Hope: Darfur Dreams of Peace. Dodd DVD 137
The Devil Came on Horseback. Dodd DVD 138
ER Darfur Story Arc, Episodes “No Place to Hide,” airdate 4/27/2006 and “There are No Angels Here,” airdate 5/4/06. Dodd DVD 139
Familiar Voices: A Reaction to the Crisis in Darfur. Dodd DVD 140
Judgment on Genocide: International Campaign for Justice in Sudan. Dodd DVD 141
The Promise. Dodd DVD 142
Stopping Genocide: Darfur (Sudan), 2004. Dodd VHS 439
They Turned Our Desert into Fire. Dodd DVD 143
Through the Eyes of Children: Growing Up in Sudan. Dodd DVD 144
Under Siege: The Nuba of Sudan. Dodd VHS 440
Witnessing Darfur: Genocide Emergency. Dodd DVD 145
Restrictions on Access
All materials listed in the finding aid are unrestricted and available for research. Some materials containing personal email addresses have been redacted. Contact the curator for further information.
Acquisition Information
The Eric Reeves Papers were donated in 2010 by Eric Reeves. Additions to the collection were received in 2011.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Personal Materials, 2002-2010
  - Articles about Eric Reeves, 2005-2006 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Certificates, 2002-2007 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2004-2008, undated (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Curriculum Vitae, 2010 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Dedication, 2005 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Event Programs, 2001-2007, undated (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Guide to people referred to in email, 2010 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Letters of recommendation, 2002 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, 2000-2005, undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Sudan Aid Fund, 2010 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Travel Documents, 2003 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
- Series II: Writings, 1996-2011
  - Articles by Eric Reeves, 1996-2003 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Articles by Eric Reeves, 2004 (Box 1:, Folder 13-15)
  - Articles by Eric Reeves, 2005 (Box 2:, Folder 16-17)
  - Articles by Eric Reeves, 2006 (Box 2:, Folder 18)
  - Articles by Eric Reeves, 2007 (Box 2:, Folder 19)
  - Articles by Eric Reeves, 2008 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
  - Articles by Eric Reeves, 2009 (Box 2:, Folder 21)
  - Articles by Eric Reeves, 2010 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
  - Book Project Proposal, 2004-2005 (Box 3:, Folder 23)
  - Correspondence, 2001-2004 (Box 3:, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, undated, 2004-2011 (Box 3:, Folder 25)
  - Email Correspondence, 2000 (Box 3:, Folder 26)
  - Email Correspondence, 2001 (Box 3:, Folder 27)
  - Email Correspondence, 2002 (Box 3:, Folder 28)
  - Email Correspondence, 2003 (Box 3:, Folder 29)
  - Email Correspondence, 2004 (Box 3:, Folder 30-31)
  - Email Correspondence, 2005 (Box 3:, Folder 32-33)
  - Email Correspondence, 2006 (Box 4:, Folder 34-35)
  - Email Correspondence, 2007 (Box 4:, Folder 36)
  - Email Correspondence, 2008 (Box 4:, Folder 37)
  - Email Correspondence, 2009 (Box 4:, Folder 38)
  - Email Correspondence, 2010 (Box 4:, Folder 39)
  - Email Correspondence, 2011 (Box 4:, Folder 40)
  - Email Correspondence, undated (Box 4:, Folder 41)
  - Lectures, 2004-2007 (Box 5:, Folder 42)
  - Letters to the Editor, 2004-2007 (Box 5:, Folder 43)
  - List of Acronyms/ Terminology for Sudan, 2010 (Box 5:, Folder 44)
  - List of Publications by Reeves, 2004 (Box 5:, Folder 45)
  - Notebooks from Travel to Sudan, 2003 (Box 5:, Folder 46)
  - Testimony of Eric Reeves to the Massachusetts State Legislature, 2005 Nov 17 (Box 5:, Folder 47)
  - Writing: "A War on Terrorism and the Betrayal of Southern Sudan", 2001 (Box 5:, Folder 48)
  - Writing: "The Agony of Internal Exile: Sudan's Displaced Populations in a World of Differences", undated (Box 5:, Folder 49)
- Series III: Research Files, 1999-2009
  - 90-day Humanitarian Action Plan for Darfur, 2004 (Box 5:, Folder 50)
  - ACAS Bulletin, 2000-2003 (Box 5:, Folder 51)
  - Agreement Documents, 2003-2004, undated (Box 5:, Folder 52)
  - Arms Trade, 2003 (Box 5:, Folder 53)
  - Articles, 2001-2004 (Box 5:, Folder 54)
  - Articles, 2006 (Box 5:, Folder 55)
  - Congressional Correspondence, 2000-2004 (Box 5:, Folder 56)
  - Congressional Testimony and Bills, 2001-2007 (Box 5:, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence cc'd to Reeves, 1999-2002 (Box 5:, Folder 58)
  - Darfur Mortality Updates, 2004-2005 (Box 6:, Folder 59)
  - Divestment Campaigns, 2005-2006 (Box 6:, Folder 60)
  - Draft Peace Agreement, 2004 (Box 6:, Folder 61)
  - E-mails from Sudan–L listserv, 1999 (Box 6:, Folder 62)
  - Genocide Olympics Campaign, 2007-2008 (Box 6:, Folder 63)
  - Human Rights Watch Report: Sudan, Oil, and Human Rights Part 1, 2003 (Box 6:, Folder 64)
  - Human Rights Watch Report: Sudan, Oil, and Human Rights Part 2, 2003 (Box 6:, Folder 65)
  - Human Rights Watch Report: Sudan, Oil, and Human Rights Part 3, 2003 (Box 6:, Folder 66)
  - ISG Newsletter, 2004-2005 (Box 6:, Folder 67)
  - Memorandum of Understanding between the Government of Sudan and the SPLM/A, 2002 (Box 6:, Folder 68)
  - Memorandum between the Government of Sudan and the U.N. Security Council, 2004 (Box 6:, Folder 69)
  - Memorandum: Mass Graves in Darfur, 2004 (Box 6:, Folder 70)
  - Most Wanted Perpetrators, 2005, undated (Box 6:, Folder 71)
  - National Democractic Alliance, Sudan, 2001 (Box 6:, Folder 72)
  - News Articles, 1999-2004 (Box 6:, Folder 73)
  - News Articles, 2004-2005 (Box 6:, Folder 74)
  - Olympics, 2008 (Box 6:, Folder 75)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 6:, Folder 76)
  - Photographs from the Nuba Mountains, Southern Sudan, 2003 (Box 6:, Folder 77)
  - Physicians for Human Rights, 2007-2009 (Box 6:, Folder 78)
  - Physicians for Human Rights Press Releases, 2004 (Box 6:, Folder 79)
  - Protocols, 2004 (Box 6:, Folder 80)
  - Reports, 2004 (Box 7:, Folder 81)
  - Rwanda, 1994-1999 (Box 7:, Folder 82)
  - Statements, 2004 (Box 7:, Folder 83)
  - Sudan Timeline, 2004 (Box 7:, Folder 84)
  - Talisman Energy, Inc., 1999-2004 (Box 7:, Folder 85)
  - Transcript of Oil Evidence, 2005 (Box 7:, Folder 86)
  - U.S. Institute for Peace, undated (Box 7:, Folder 87)
  - United Nations Documents, 2004-2005 (Box 7:, Folder 88)
  - Writing: Sudan: Suffering a Long Way Off, undated (Box 7:, Folder 89)
  - Case Files: Presbyterian Church of Sudan et. al, vs. Talisman Energy, Inc., 2002 (Box 7:, Folder 90)
  - Case Files: Presbyterian Church of Sudan et. al, vs. Talisman Energy, Inc., 2003 (Box 7:, Folder 91)
  - Case Files: Presbyterian Church of Sudan et. al, vs. Talisman Energy, Inc., undated (Box 7:, Folder 92)
  - Case Files: Presbyterian Church of Sudan et. al, vs. Talisman Energy, Inc., undated (Box 7:, Folder 93)
- Series IV: Oversize Materials, 2004-2008
  - Scrapbooks, undated (Box 8)
  - Genocide Olympics T-shirt, 2008 (Box 8)
  - Farchana Manifesto Poster, undated (Box 8)
- Series V: Audiovisual Materials, undated [2004-2011]
  - Cassette tapes of radio interviews with Eric Reeves, undated (Box 9)
  - Photographs from Sudan on CD, undated (Box 9)
  - Documents and Maps of Sudan on CD, undated (Box 9)